<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <title>Welcome to Podcast University!</title>
  <slug>welcome-to-podcast-university</slug>
  <author></author>
  <pubDate>2015-02-25 20:39:25</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2015-02-25 20:39:25</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently, a very good friend of mine &lt;em&gt;(&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/richieclarkie" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;@richieclarkie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;)&lt;/em&gt; decided to return to the IT industry after a 15 year absence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clearly a 15 year hiatus, is significant in any industry, but especially pertaining to IT, it is arguably exceptional.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Whilst there will always be some &lt;em&gt;core fundamentals&lt;/em&gt; to the IT industry, in truth, he is in many ways, starting over.&amp;nbsp; However, I'm happy to report, he is extremely energised and keen to get back into a more &lt;strong&gt;'operations'&lt;/strong&gt; driving seat.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Knowing I have a near obsessive interest in listening to technical podcasts, he asked me for some suggestions; hence this blog post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;The New Age Of Education&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;We live in a time where there is a wealth of educational information, freely available online. Whether using one of the more formal teaching platforms like &lt;a href="http://www.codecademy.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Khan Academy&lt;/a&gt;, or just &lt;em&gt;tuning&lt;/em&gt; into one of the many excellent and often extremely professional podcasts available, these resources can at the very least, be a huge compliment to formal education - some could even argue a replacement!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Whatever your opinion, it’s difficult to disagree with the fact that &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of these resources, are unbelievably useful for keeping up to speed with this frantically evolving world, we call ‘&lt;strong&gt;IT’&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Podcatcher Of Choice&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are many systems available for listening to podcasts, but my current personal &lt;em&gt;‘podcatcher of choice’&lt;/em&gt; is the excellent &lt;a href="http://www.shiftyjelly.com/pocketcasts" target="_blank"&gt;Pocket Casts&lt;/a&gt; app.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I often have the podcast playback &lt;strong&gt;speeded &lt;/strong&gt;up 1.3 times – &lt;em&gt;the app is clever&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;enough to not raise the pitch, yet enables me to get through shows a little quicker.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Also, a lot of podcasts have adverts - pressing the forward button on the Pocket Casts app, quickly advances the podcast by 30 seconds – very handy!  &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Podcast List&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Below is a list of the more 'technical' podcasts that I listen to on a regular basis &lt;em&gt;(at the time of writing),&lt;/em&gt; along with a brief description and personal opinion.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://hanselminutes.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Hanselminutes&lt;/a&gt; – General technical content, but primarily web development - this is my top choice - I haven't missed an episode in about 4 years!  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.dotnetrocks.com/" target="_blank"&gt;DotNet Rocks&lt;/a&gt; - General technical content, but primarily web development - this is probably my next favourite - I dip into these - listen to a couple a week.  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.runasradio.com/" target="_blank"&gt;RunAs Radio&lt;/a&gt; – General operations &amp;amp; sys admin content - I dip into these - probably listen to one every few weeks.  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://shoptalkshow.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Shoptalk Show&lt;/a&gt; - All front end web development (CSS, JavaScript etc) - I listen to this each week.  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.codingblocks.net/" target="_blank"&gt;Coding Blocks&lt;/a&gt; - All development &lt;em&gt;(really good, but quite advanced)&lt;/em&gt; - I listen to this as and when they release.  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/digitalp" target="_blank"&gt;BBC Click&lt;/a&gt; - General technical content - I dip into this if the title looks interesting.  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://herdingcode.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Herding Code&lt;/a&gt; – General coding content - I listen to this as and when they release.  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.se-radio.net/" target="_blank"&gt;Software Engineering Radio&lt;/a&gt; - All programming content - I listen to this occasionally – in truth, it can be quite &lt;em&gt;dry&lt;/em&gt;, but often contains a few gems!  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://devchat.tv/js-jabber/" target="_blank"&gt;JavaScript Jabber&lt;/a&gt; – JavaScript panel discussion - I listen to this every week.  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://devchat.tv/adventures-in-angular" target="_blank"&gt;Adventures in Angular&lt;/a&gt; - AngularJS &lt;em&gt;(JavaScript)&lt;/em&gt; panel discussion - I listen to this every week. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are numerous other podcasts that I sample on occasion, ranging from the &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.defensivesecurity.org/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defensive Security&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; podcast to the &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.codenewbie.org/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;CodeNewbie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; podcast, but I listen to these less frequently.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;…A Little Extra!&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;It’s probably worth mentioning that I also subscribe to the below weekly newsletters, which again, I can highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://html5weekly.com/" target="_blank"&gt;HTML5 Weekly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://javascriptweekly.com/" target="_blank"&gt;JavaScript Weekly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://webtoolsweekly.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Web Tools Weekly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://webopsweekly.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Web Operations Weekly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hopefully, you may just spot something of interest in this blog post!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories>
    <category>Blog</category>
    <category>Rambling</category>
    <category>SysAdmin</category>
    <category>DevOps</category>
    <category>Website</category>
  </categories>
  <comments></comments>
</post>