<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <title>Office 365, Outlook &amp; attachments</title>
  <slug>office-365-outlook--attachments</slug>
  <author></author>
  <pubDate>2016-01-17 13:22:59</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2016-03-08 16:27:02</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently, we received rather confusing claims from specific users, stating they were receiving certain emails, often &lt;u&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;days&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/u&gt; after they had been sent.&amp;nbsp; This behavior was not consistent across the user base.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Great – inconsistent errors; don’t you just love them?!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Without dissecting the ins and outs of exchange message tracking in this post, suffice to say, it became clear that there &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; anything technically wrong with the message flow mechanism; it had the hallmarks that emails were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; being sent from the client at the time the user thought. &lt;p&gt;Due to time constraints and slightly inconsistent information, this was unfortunately allowed to fester for far too long, without a satisfactory conclusion.  &lt;h2&gt;Replicating the Process&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Eventually, as expected, the issue raised its head again &lt;i&gt;(albeit in a slightly different context).&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp; This time, both I and the user sending the emails, were in a better position to analyse behavior.  &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When I saw the process being used, it jumped out at me instantly, what problem was.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;hr align="center" size="0" width="100%"&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Some Workflow Facts&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;This user primarily &lt;em&gt;(although not all the time)&lt;/em&gt; uses the web based, Office 365 Mail as their preferred method of sending emails – perfectly acceptable; indeed encouraged in some environments.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;This user, when sending attachments from Word, uses the ‘Share’ options from within Word to ‘Send as Attachment’ &lt;em&gt;(not the process I use, but again, perfectly acceptable).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://normansolutions.co.uk/posts/files/948dded5-4f41-4421-848f-133b9735fc32.png"&gt;&lt;img title="image" style="border-top: 0px; border-right: 0px; background-image: none; border-bottom: 0px; padding-top: 0px; padding-left: 0px; border-left: 0px; display: inline; padding-right: 0px" border="0" alt="image" src="https://normansolutions.co.uk/posts/files/1e505bf2-57c7-406b-ad34-f85b2c600753.png" width="516" height="198"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;It appears that when using this option to send attachments, if you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have the native client version of Outlook running, no email is sent. &lt;p&gt;As soon as the user opened up Outlook &lt;em&gt;(the client)&lt;/em&gt; – the email went! &lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let’s be clear, this end user wasn’t doing &lt;i&gt;anything&lt;/i&gt; wrong, they were correctly using in-built functionality to perform a task.&amp;nbsp; They are not expected to know that Outlook needs to be running.&amp;nbsp; Alas, there is also no appropriate dialog box feedback from Word, explaining this.  &lt;p&gt;Of course, I subsequently demonstrated that the web version of Office 365, was indeed just a webpage &lt;i&gt;(agreed, a phenomenal webpage, but nevertheless, a webpage) - W&lt;/i&gt;ord doesn’t know about this webpage and is expecting to use the inbuilt Outlook program. &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Lessons learnt:&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Ensure that you &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; see the entire process from the end user’s perspective.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Never assume that everyone performs daily tasks, in the same way that you do!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Of course having been in this industry for well over 15 years – this is nothing new; but clearly some lessons need to have time put aside, and &lt;em&gt;re-learnt &lt;img class="wlEmoticon wlEmoticon-smile" style="border-top-style: none; border-bottom-style: none; border-right-style: none; border-left-style: none" alt="Smile" src="https://normansolutions.co.uk/posts/files/d25b9746-a873-4858-8933-820a868358ac.png"&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories>
    <category>Office 365</category>
    <category>SysAdmin</category>
    <category>QuickTip</category>
  </categories>
  <comments></comments>
</post>