<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <title>Good enough? Don’t answer that!</title>
  <slug>good-enough-dont-answer-that</slug>
  <author></author>
  <pubDate>2013-12-27 17:34:12</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2013-12-27 17:34:12</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite blog posts is “&lt;a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/ImAPhonyAreYou.aspx" target="_blank"&gt;I'm a phony. Are you?&lt;/a&gt;” by Scott Hanselman.&amp;nbsp; I was on holiday in France &lt;a href="http://www.glomel.co.uk" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;(here to be exact)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, when I read this post, and it gave me a wonderful sense of relief - I highly encourage you to read it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Monsieur Hanselman has in many ways, been like an unofficial virtual mentor for myself; I regularly listen to the &lt;a href="http://hanselminutes.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Hanselminutes&lt;/a&gt; podcast, and again, highly recommend it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The fact is, that despite having been “fiddling” with computer programming since I was 12 years old &lt;em&gt;(starting on a &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharp_MZ#MZ-80K_group" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharp MZ-80K&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; - which my father still owns!) - &lt;/em&gt;I never really fitted the conventional stereotype of a &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/users/22656/jon-skeet" target="_blank"&gt;maths driven computer geek&lt;/a&gt; - in the late 80’s and 90’s this didn’t really encourage “one” to embrace IT with real confidence!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;In truth, I fit the classic “Jack of all trades” rather than a “Master of one”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;I have a serious thirst for knowledge - true, not &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; an ability to master it, but definitely to acquire it.&amp;nbsp; Over time, I have realised that this benefits me on several levels; whether I am just being the “family Google”&lt;em&gt; (for school homework assistance),&lt;/em&gt; or engaging in conversation with someone, be it about &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Equal_temperament" target="_blank"&gt;Equal Temperament&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Hardy" target="_blank"&gt;Thomas Hardy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Einstein" target="_blank"&gt;Einstein&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Jam" target="_blank"&gt;The Jam&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Letters-Extreme-Pilgrim-Reflections-Life/dp/1846041333" target="_blank"&gt;Spiritual Meditation&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Hastings" target="_blank"&gt;the Battle of Hastings&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Offside_(association_football)" target="_blank"&gt;Offside Rule&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;(ok…maybe &lt;u&gt;not&lt;/u&gt; the offside rule - that’s pushing it), &lt;/em&gt;but you get the idea, a variety of knowledge comes with benefits.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;“Jack of all”&lt;/em&gt; also applies to my musical abilities; whilst I can play the piano, guitar, bass, vocals and enjoy song-writing to a reasonable level, I am definitely no &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfgang_Amadeus_Mozart" target="_blank"&gt;Mozart&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_Dylan" target="_blank"&gt;Dylan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, a side benefit of being “&lt;em&gt;Jack&lt;/em&gt;” is that it has enabled me to experience a vast array of different musical experiences, ranging from performances at the world famous &lt;a href="http://www.themarqueeclub.net/" target="_blank"&gt;Marquee Club&lt;/a&gt; through to working as a semi-professional touring musician, knocking up several hundred gigs over the past 25 years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Living the dream man! - well sort of….&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;font color="#666666"&gt;&lt;em&gt;At this point - the obligatory home music video!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;iframe height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/_VSJ2_igkic" frameborder="0" width="640" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Ok – you didn’t feel like a computer genius, your point being?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;My point, is that because I never felt I was a “&lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;” computer &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Turing" target="_blank"&gt;genius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;I initially shied away from taking any huge jump of confidence into the IT industry, for fear of ritual humiliation.&amp;nbsp; To be fair, I made further headway into the music industry, before eventually realising that I needed to eat –&lt;em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;financial success in music is hard!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With hindsight, I realised that by gaining experience working in several “other” industries &lt;em&gt;(legal, retail etc), &lt;/em&gt;enjoying the opposite side of the IT fence for a few years - in short, being a “real” end user - provided me with a surprising empathy and ability to assist customers, especially in my early days of IT support; I understood where they were coming from - something that I do occasionally see lacking in a lot of technicians, who have never worked &lt;em&gt;outside &lt;/em&gt;of IT.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Times_They_Are_a-Changin'" target="_blank"&gt;The times, they are a-changin!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;With the benefit of age &lt;em&gt;(oh yes, there are some, trust me!),&lt;/em&gt; being a father, having an amazingly inspiring and encouraging wife, combined with a sheer “&lt;em&gt;what the heck&lt;/em&gt;” attitude, I now embrace the knowledge and experience that I &lt;strong&gt;know I have&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;nbsp; I feel confident to help others, develop products and to engage in technical debate &lt;em&gt;(on differing levels),&lt;/em&gt; where required; but &lt;u&gt;crucially&lt;/u&gt;, I am also very happy to acknowledge when I &lt;em&gt;&lt;u&gt;don’t&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/em&gt; know something - &lt;em&gt;that’s a lot harder and indeed rarer, than you think!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, to summarise; I eventually re-joined the IT world many moons ago, when it was still to some extent, a rather arrogant industry &lt;em&gt;(pre &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dot-com_bubble" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;dot com bubble&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;) -&lt;/em&gt; where a technical employee with very little &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; knowledge and experience, could secure a lucrative position, just by knowing a little more than the person who employed them.&amp;nbsp; A time where “arrogance” and “hostility” were almost required credentials!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Luckily, an industry that I love, is becoming much more responsible, respectable, accepting and less patronising.&amp;nbsp; It does have a long way to go &lt;em&gt;(I still meet those “con-men” who love to try and “blind with science” -&amp;nbsp; and it’s always nice to challenge them).&amp;nbsp; &lt;/em&gt;It also needs to embrace and encourage both genders equally &lt;em&gt;(there are still far too few women working in IT) -&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;u&gt;but&lt;/u&gt; it has made serious progress &lt;a href="http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/IMHO" target="_blank"&gt;IMHO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, to the title of the post - yes, possibly at times, you may indeed not feel good enough, and possibly, at times, you don’t want to hear that - &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; be under no illusion - this is a great industry that encourages more than ever, &lt;strong&gt;your&lt;/strong&gt; input, &lt;strong&gt;your&lt;/strong&gt; opinion and &lt;strong&gt;your&lt;/strong&gt; knowledge, as well as continuing to &lt;em&gt;offer&lt;/em&gt; you, it’s output, opinion and knowledge &lt;em&gt;(it never stops turning, and you never stop learning – &lt;u&gt;whatever your age&lt;/u&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simply put - I would &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; not be working in, and enjoying the industry I love, if it were the same “beast” that it was in the 80’s and 90’s – &lt;em&gt;so bring on 2014!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;My weekly podcast &lt;em&gt;(dog walking material!) &lt;/em&gt;list for education and inspiration&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://hanselminutes.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Hanselminutes&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.dotnetrocks.com/" target="_blank"&gt;DotNet Rocks&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qykl" target="_blank"&gt;BBC - In Our Time&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/digitalp" target="_blank"&gt;BBC – Click&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.thetabletshow.com/" target="_blank"&gt;The Tablet Show&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://shoptalkshow.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Shop Talk Show&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://herdingcode.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Herding Code&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qy05" target="_blank"&gt;BBC - Thinking Allowed&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006s6p6" target="_blank"&gt;BBC - Beyond Belief&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.thisamericanlife.org/" target="_blank"&gt;This American Life&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://thisdeveloperslife.com/" target="_blank"&gt;This Developer’s Life&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://javascriptjabber.com/" target="_blank"&gt;JavaScript Jabber&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.se-radio.net/" target="_blank"&gt;Software Engineering Radio&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/fricomedy" target="_blank"&gt;BBC Friday Night Comedy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories>
    <category>Blog</category>
    <category>Website</category>
    <category>Rambling</category>
  </categories>
  <comments></comments>
</post>