<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <title>Presentation, Nerves and Videotape</title>
  <slug>presentation-nerves-videotape</slug>
  <author></author>
  <pubDate>2014-03-28 20:11:25</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2015-07-29 01:19:31</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I had the privileged of being asked to give a ‘&lt;em&gt;show and tell’&lt;/em&gt; style presentation, at the Firefly Developer’s Day, held at &lt;a href="http://www.radley.org.uk/Home.aspx" target="_blank"&gt;Radley College&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In truth, I received this invitation with a mixture of pride and anxiety – visions springing to mind of the &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_tqRyzTvNKE" target="_blank"&gt;Michael Bay &lt;em&gt;‘meltdown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;’ &lt;/em&gt;during his presentation at CES 2014!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, I love debates of all natures &lt;em&gt;(just ask my colleagues &amp;amp; family &lt;img class="wlEmoticon wlEmoticon-smile" style="border-top-style: none; border-bottom-style: none; border-right-style: none; border-left-style: none" alt="Smile" src="https://normansolutions.co.uk/posts/files/c32c627c-4f55-43d6-aa8c-49ee9c1f0c66.png"&gt;)&lt;/em&gt; and certainly feel confident in my chosen subject area.&amp;nbsp; Indeed, in a ‘previous life’ my primary role was working as a software trainer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why heck, I’ve done hundreds of musical gigs over the past 25 years or so (albeit in the comfort of a band environment); but a crowd isn’t completely alien to me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;However&lt;/strong&gt;, it’s always slightly &lt;em&gt;scary&lt;/em&gt; when you don’t &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; know your audience or the quality of technical support that’s there to back you up!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I have always prided myself on doing the best I can, in whatever I do – I’m not claiming to be a perfectionist by any means, but I like to do a good job.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Although, in truth this was a relatively &lt;em&gt;small&lt;/em&gt; gathering of technically minded folk, I still wanted to give it my best shot.&amp;nbsp; As such, I took advice from several people, that had more experience of public speaking than me &lt;em&gt;(particular thanks to &lt;a href="http://www.st-marys-shaftesbury.co.uk/Theatre-Studies" target="_blank"&gt;Chris Sykes – the Drama Teacher at St Mary’s School, Shaftesbury&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;So, a plan of action was established &lt;em&gt;(...sort of)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Presentation must have &lt;strong&gt;credibility&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;em&gt;I have witnessed too many IT presentations in the past, which attempt to ‘blind with science’ in order to mask a clear lack of subject knowledge &lt;img class="wlEmoticon wlEmoticon-steamingmad" style="border-top-style: none; border-bottom-style: none; border-right-style: none; border-left-style: none" alt="Steaming mad" src="https://normansolutions.co.uk/posts/files/edb56c52-f8fb-48dc-9e65-712be5a6f4af.png"&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Must be passionate and engaging&lt;em&gt; (well, as much as you can be, in such circumstances).&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Allow for technical fall-back &lt;strike&gt;if things go wrong&lt;/strike&gt; &lt;em&gt;expect &lt;/em&gt;things to go wrong &lt;img class="wlEmoticon wlEmoticon-smile" style="border-top-style: none; border-bottom-style: none; border-right-style: none; border-left-style: none" alt="Smile" src="https://normansolutions.co.uk/posts/files/c32c627c-4f55-43d6-aa8c-49ee9c1f0c66.png"&gt;.  &lt;li&gt;Have a back-up strategy for stage nerves.  &lt;li&gt;Rehearse, rehearse and then rehearse again.  &lt;li&gt;Test, test and then test again.  &lt;li&gt;Did I say ‘&lt;em&gt;test’&lt;/em&gt;?  &lt;li&gt;Did I say &lt;em&gt;‘rehearse’&lt;/em&gt;?  &lt;li&gt;Oh yes, and &lt;em&gt;breathe&lt;/em&gt;!  &lt;li&gt;Post presentation review.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Overkill?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some may say this is a little overkill for a small presentation, but I would disagree.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Indeed, I even went so far as to pre-record screen cast video’s of all the demos used in the presentation, just in case of internet failure&lt;em&gt; (as funny enough, that happens occasionally).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For a bit of sparkle, I also took the opportunity to use the browser based presentation framework &lt;a href="http://lab.hakim.se/reveal-js/#/" target="_blank"&gt;revealJS&lt;/a&gt; in an attempt to break away from &lt;strong&gt;death by PowerPoint&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;nbsp; Ironically, I received more comments about this, than anything else &lt;em&gt;(I don’t know if that’s a good or bad thing).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I rehearsed the talk several times, and also maintained a good old fashioned ‘paper’ crib sheet – &lt;em&gt;yes you read that correctly, paper!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Summary and Video!&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;This may just be a rambling about a ‘small town’ IT presentation, but I am glad to report that the event went rather well, as did the Firefly Developer’s Day in general.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I certainly didn’t &lt;em&gt;‘die on stage’ - technically or emotionally &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;(which is always a bonus),&lt;/em&gt; and I hope a few nuggets of information were successfully dispensed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Clearly, there is always room for improvement, which I shall endeavour to make.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the quality of the video footage from the presentation is rather poor, but Firefly were kind enough to provide me with a copy, for post presentation critique!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As such, to complete the blog post, I have included this below &lt;em&gt;(warts and all)&lt;/em&gt; along with a link to the revealJS presentation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;iframe height="280" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/90117744?byline=0" frameborder="0" width="500" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;p&gt;Presentation: &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/ffdemonstration" target="_blank"&gt;http://bit.ly/ffdemonstration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;font size="2"&gt;(Sincere thanks to Firefly for giving me the stage; to Radley College ICT department, who provided excellent and seamless support, and to my fellow attendees of the Firefly Developer’s Day, who were very kind in their reception)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories>
    <category>Rambling</category>
    <category>VLE</category>
    <category>Firefly</category>
  </categories>
  <comments>
  </comments>
</post>