<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <title>Dip your toe into a little SASS!</title>
  <slug>dip-your-toe-into-a-little-sass</slug>
  <author></author>
  <pubDate>2014-05-22 21:26:43</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2014-05-23 15:09:08</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;Ok…I get the whole &lt;a href="http://www.urbaninsight.com/2012/04/12/ten-reasons-you-should-be-using-css-preprocessor" target="_blank"&gt;CSS pre-processor&lt;/a&gt; movement; I don’t need convincing of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it is so good.&amp;nbsp; However, what I do need, is a justification to invest time into learning &lt;em&gt;yet another&lt;/em&gt; technology!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is certainly no lack of resources available, for these little beauty's (&lt;a href="http://lesscss.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Less&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="http://sass-lang.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Sass&lt;/a&gt;): but then there’s a problem for a start – &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;which one&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;?&amp;nbsp; Try &lt;a href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=less+or+sass" target="_blank"&gt;Googling that&lt;/a&gt;, and you will soon discover, many opinions &lt;img class="wlEmoticon wlEmoticon-smile" style="border-top-style: none; border-bottom-style: none; border-right-style: none; border-left-style: none" alt="Smile" src="https://normansolutions.co.uk/posts/files/9c01fbb5-8fe8-4141-b7a6-7bc2cf24663f.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the past, I have ‘tinkered’ with &lt;strong&gt;Less&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(primarily because this was being supported by the excellent &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="http://vswebessentials.com/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Web Essentials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;),&lt;/em&gt; and for the most part, I found it extremely useful.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That said, I kept catching myself jumping back into those good old CSS files to make tweaking changes, which sort of defeated the object - old habits and all that!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;To cut a long story short – I recently discovered that Web Essentials, now &lt;a href="http://webessentials.uservoice.com/forums/140520-general/suggestions/3140436-support-for-sass-scss" target="_blank"&gt;supports Sass&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; Right or wrong, I do get the impression that Sass &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; pips Less to the post &lt;em&gt;(although I must stress, I’m no authority on the subject).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As such, I thought I would have a go with Sass.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Creating a base template&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Whenever I start any project, I always like to go and get the latest versions of the tools, libraries and frameworks that I will be using – it just helps produce that nice “&lt;strong&gt;fresh start&lt;/strong&gt;” feeling.&amp;nbsp; This could be &lt;a href="http://getbootstrap.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://jquery.com/" target="_blank"&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://fortawesome.github.io/Font-Awesome/" target="_blank"&gt;Font Awesome,&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://timeago.yarp.com/" target="_blank"&gt;timeago,&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.primebox.co.uk/projects/jquery-cookiebar/" target="_blank"&gt;CookieBar&lt;/a&gt; or a myriad of other scripts &lt;em&gt;(either self-written or open source etc).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I also like to build into my templates, appropriate CDN fall-backs; be it jQuery or Bootsrap etc, ensuring the best of both worlds (speed and robustness).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Part of this setting up process, is also to establish a nice CSS base &lt;em&gt;(&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://necolas.github.io/normalize.css/" target="_blank"&gt;normalise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; etc).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;So this is me dipping my toe!&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;I believe consistency is a prime factor when building websites&lt;em&gt; (we’ve all seen those earlier CMS driven sites, that allowed for end user ‘&lt;strong&gt;Word Art&lt;/strong&gt;’ styling on each page – arghhh!).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Recently, I have also become extremely aware of the importance of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Style_guide" target="_blank"&gt;Style Guides&lt;/a&gt;, especially when it comes to colours and fonts.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is where Sass &lt;em&gt;(or indeed Less)&lt;/em&gt; are brilliant; you can provide a variable name to a colour, and then use that variable throughout your styles – want to change the colour throughout the style sheet? Easy - just change the variable value.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can even lighten or darken the colour by a specific percentage, possibly for a &lt;strong&gt;hover&lt;/strong&gt; style, thus ensuring you keep within the boundaries of that base colour theme.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;My first recommendation, would be to go and grab a copy of &lt;a href="http://richbray.me/cms/" target="_blank"&gt;Color Me SASS&lt;/a&gt; – this in an excellent resource of &lt;em&gt;established&lt;/em&gt; colour names and their equivalent hex codes.&amp;nbsp; This library &lt;em&gt;(if that is what you call it)&lt;/em&gt; also demonstrates great use of another brilliant benefit with CSS pre-processors – &lt;strong&gt;modularisation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With Sass, you can &lt;em&gt;(indeed are encouraged)&lt;/em&gt; to completely separate your files into specific modules responsible for targeted areas of styling – to be fair, you can of course do this with conventional CSS, but it somehow feels ‘&lt;em&gt;better’&lt;/em&gt; with Sass.&amp;nbsp; In the &lt;em&gt;‘Color Me Sass’&lt;/em&gt; example, each colour shade type, is split into it’s own Sass style sheet, and then all pulled into one single sheet using &lt;a href="http://sass-lang.com/guide" target="_blank"&gt;@import&lt;/a&gt; statements.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@import statements are excellent – similar to CSS imports, &lt;strong&gt;except&lt;/strong&gt; you end up with one single style sheet – and I don’t need to express the benefits of that, in terms of speed and efficiency!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Some basic customisation&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;I chose to add some &lt;em&gt;small&lt;/em&gt; additions to the ‘Color Me’ Sass sheet, in order to provide basic percentage shade changes, as below:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;script gitsrc="https://gist.github.com/normansolutions/73f7d82d5afaa0425db1.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/normansolutions/73f7d82d5afaa0425db1"&gt;Click for code snippet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This addition, allowed me to use a 10% colour lightening &amp;amp; darkening, on a cookie bar feature I was using; literally I just entered appropriate variables &lt;em&gt;($greenDarkening10 etc) &lt;/em&gt;into my ‘CookieBar’ Sass sheet, to style that element – rather than setting a fixed colour.&amp;nbsp; This way, if I ever need to change the cookie bar styling, I just change the base variable value – perfect reusability!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;script gitsrc="https://gist.github.com/normansolutions/e285faccb28a34307cb9.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/normansolutions/e285faccb28a34307cb9"&gt;Click for code snippet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Build tool&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;As I mentioned earlier, I am using the brilliant &lt;a href="http://vswebessentials.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Web Essentials tool&lt;/a&gt;, which provides a nice automatic compilation of my Sass files to conventional CSS.&amp;nbsp; All ready for &lt;em&gt;minification&lt;/em&gt;– of course!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;hr&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sass and Less both contain a ton of amazing features.&amp;nbsp; Some are extremely simple &lt;em&gt;(but equally very useful), &lt;/em&gt;much like the above variable example; whereas others can be vastly complex and quite mind-blowing!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I have come to realise, that you don’t &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to be up and running with these more advanced features immediately; just using colour variables alone, can be of huge benefit.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Using these tools, I believe, also encourages the use of important best practices, such as modularisation, design consistency as well as offering component reusability - which is no bad thing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I for one, am going to make a conscious effort to embrace Sass &lt;em&gt;(or Less) &lt;/em&gt;a lot more in the future; it seems foolish not to.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories>
    <category>Website</category>
    <category>CSS</category>
    <category>SASS</category>
  </categories>
  <comments></comments>
</post>